

# Carlos Ramirez III 💋

New York, United States • Member since October 29, 2014

Carlos is a professional software engineer and web developer specializing in the Ruby on Rails framework. He has been working with tech companies in New York's Silicon Alley for over 5 years, helping to build technology-based businesses from the ground up. He has a Bachelor's degree in Computer Science from Williams College and has been working in the software industry for nearly 10 years.



#### **PORTFOLIO**

# eDivv, Inc. (Contract)

Ruby on Rails, PostgreSQL, Heroku, SASS, jQuery, Stripe, Twitter Bootstrap...

# The Capital Web LLC (via Toptal)

Ruby on Rails, Heroku, Rspec, Capybara

# Nafasi (via Toptal)

Ruby on Rails, Heroku, PostgreSQL, Twitter Bootstrap, Rspec, Capybara

#### **EXPERIENCE**

Ruby, 6 years

Ruby on Rails, 6 years

Twitter Bootstrap, 4 years

**RSpec,** 6 years

Test-driven Development (TDD), 6 years

Heroku, 6 years

Back-end Development, 8 years

JavaScript, 5 years

#### **AVAILABILITY**

Unavailable

#### PREFERRED ENVIRONMENT

Nitrous.io dev environment, Vim text editor, Git

# THE MOST AMAZING...

...exciting thing I've built recently is a custom Zapier app w/ web hooks and a REST API to allow the integration of a new software service with hundreds of others

2016/10/16 **EMPLOYMENT** 

#### Web Developer, CTO

eDivv, Inc. (Contract)

2013 - PRESENT

- Implemented an online marketplace and bartering platform for trading beauty products.
- Provided post-development technical leadership to the executive and development team, including reviewing code, generating business flows and wireframes, and other consultation services.
- Identified performance bottlenecks and opportunities for optimization on the Heroku hosting platform.

Technologies: Ruby on Rails, PostgreSQL, Heroku, SASS, ¡Query, Stripe, Twitter Bootstrap, Algolia, Stamps.com, USPS

## **Technology & Business Consultant**

2016 - 2016

The Capital Web LLC (via Toptal)

- Performed a high-level evaluation of the business and product.
- Offered advice and guidance on which features to consider building based on the relative costs/benefits, timelines, etc.
- Provided recommendations on useful tools and services to help achieve business and product goals.
- Discussed startup business strategy.

Technologies: Ruby on Rails, Heroku, Rspec, Capybara

Web Developer 2015 - 2016

Nafasi (via Toptal)

- Completely re-designed the visual design of the user interface using a custom Twitter Bootstrap theme.
- Designed a LinkedIn-like profile page with in-place editing and updating using AJAX and server-side rendered templates.
- Implemented a downloadable custom PDF report using HTML-to-PDF rendering techniques to ensure proper formatting and layout of the final document.
- Instituted an automating testing policy and implemented a complete integration test suite to provide full coverage of new features.
- Added analytics tracking to the web application using Segment, Mixpanel, and Google Analytics.
- Used modern methods of social engagement such as commenting, up/down voting, etc. to allow users to engage and collaborate on application-specific items.

Technologies: Ruby on Rails, Heroku, PostgreSQL, Twitter Bootstrap, Rspec, Capybara

#### 2015 - 2015

# Web Developer

Curated (via Toptal)

- Built a custom Zapier app with triggers and actions specific to the Curated software service to allow integration with hundreds of other Zapier-supported software services.
- · Created a system for triggering and subscribing to web hooks for various application events.
- Implemented time-based, recurring, and event-triggered transactional emails containing summary reports and user-action reminders.
- Optimized the performance of click- and open-rate statistics reports using counter caches and denormalized tables rather than ad-hoc SQL queries.
- Implemented the next-generation (v2) of a legacy REST API with updated conventions, best practices, and code improvements.

Technologies: Ruby on Rails, Zapier, Mandrill, PostgreSQL, REST API

Web Developer 2015 - 2015

Buster, Inc. (Contract)

- Helped launch a fully redesigned 2nd generation of this product over a 3 month period.
- Created a custom, rules-based engine for scheduling and sending customer leads to qualified vendors within the system in order to maximize profit.
- Implemented custom front-end designs and user experience flows using SASS/CSS and JavaScript.

Technologies: Ruby on Rails, JavaScript, SASS, Heroku

Web Developer 2013 - 2015

Map-tac LLC (Contract)

- Designed and built a custom itinerary building tool and marketplace for travel professionals and their clients.
- Created a custom search algorithm for indexing and finding tours based on user criteria using Elasticsearch.
- Developed a custom tagging tool for marking trip destinations using Yahoo!'s GeoPlanet API.
- Built a white-labeled search engine front-end featuring fully data-driven theming, branding, and content curation.
- Integrated dozens of third-party data feeds from suppliers, normalizing the data to allow the search engine user experience to be consistent regardless of the content's source.

Technologies: Ruby on Rails, PostgreSQL, Elasticsearch, Heroku, SASS, CoffeeScript, ¡Query, Google Maps

# Web Developer

Affirmify, LLC (Contract)

- Designed and implemented a response management software-as-a-service system for HR professionals.
- Created a custom Wufoo-style form builder using JavaScript.
- Built a multi-tenant account system with custom subdomains for each subscriber.
- Implemented a subscription-based payment model using Chargify.

Technologies: Ruby on Rails, PostgreSQL, Heroku, SASS, ¡Query, Chargify

# **Senior Software Engineer**

2008 - 2011

**Total Computer Software** 

- Designed and implemented a system-wide data searching algorithm and accompanying user interface.
- Architected and implemented an inter-agency data sharing system using C#, the .NET framework, and Windows Communication Foundation with an emphasis on interoperability, distributability, and security.
- Designed and implemented a mapping system integrated with ESRI ArcGIS web services to display maps, locate addresses, and retrieve geo-data.
- Discovered and corrected architectural design flaws to improve program efficiency and performance.
- Maintained a data-driven user interface validation system to enforce good data input.
- Handled user interface development using Windows Presentation Foundation.

Technologies: .NET

#### Curated (Development)

http://curated.co

A software-as-a-service platform for creating, managing, and sending beautifully curated newsletters.

#### Nafasi (Development)

http://nafasi.co

A platform to facilitate engagement, collaboration, and discovery between innovators and talented job seekers.

#### **Buster (Development)**

https://www.buster.com

An Uber-style marketplace for group transportation. Allows consumers to book limos, buses, vans, etc., and provides back-office tools for transportation providers to manage inventory, accept bookings, and charge customers.

#### eDivv (Development)

http://www.edivv.com

An online marketplace for trading beauty products.

# Affirmify (Development)

A response management system for HR professionals.

# **Tripwing (Development)**

http://tripwing.com

An itinerary builder and online marketplace for travel professionals and their clients.

# Keep Calm And Transition To A New Development Team (Publication)

https://www.toptal.com/software/onboarding-a-new-development-team



Many product owners don't have a technical background and thus often find themselves unprepared and scrambling when it comes time to bring on a new development team. This often results in hindered progress, wasted time, and frustration for everyone involved. If this sounds like it could be you, either now or in the future, then you should be somewhat concerned. In this blog post, Toptal Freelance Software Engineer Carlos Ramirez III will walk you through the various steps of a typical transition process in project management so you can prepare for this eventuality and make the transition as smooth as possible.

#### How to Use Rails Helpers: A Bootstrap Carousel Demonstration (Publication)

https://www.toptal.com/ruby-on-rails/rails-helper-bootstrap-carousel



One of the most misused, misunderstood, and neglected of all the Rails built-in structures is the view helper. Helpers often get a bad reputation for being a dumping ground for one-off methods used across the entire application's view layer. But what if your helpers could be more semantic, better organized, and even reusable across projects? What if they could be more than just one-off functions sprinkled throughout the view, but powerful methods that generated complex markup with ease leaving your views free of conditional logic and code? Let's see how to do this when building an image carousel, with the familiar Twitter Bootstrap framework

and some good old-fashioned object-oriented programming.

#### **SKILLS**

#### Languages

Ruby, SCSS, SASS, CSS, SQL, CoffeeScript, HTML5, Haml, JavaScript

#### Frameworks

Ruby on Rails, Bootstrap 3.0, Twitter Bootstrap, Slim, minitest, Bootstrap, Foundation

#### Libraries/APIs

JSON REST API, Ruby on Rails API, REST API, jQuery, Ruby Page Object, Segment.io, Stripe, Chargify, React.js, SQLite, Yahoo! API, API, GitHub API, Mandrill, Facebook API

#### **Tools**

GitHub, ERB, RSpec, Basecamp, Slack, Trello, Zapier, Git, Pivotal Tracker, Campfire, Sublime Text, Solr, VirtualBox, Vagrant, Asana, MailChimp

# **Paradigms**

Test-driven Development (TDD), Unit Testing, Minimum Viable Product, Lean Startups, Plain Old Ruby Object (PORO), Object-oriented Programming (OOP), MVC, REST, Agile Software Development, AJAX, Functional programming

#### **Platforms**

Heroku, Mac OS X, Amazon Web Services (AWS)

#### Misc

Mixpanel, Back-end Development, Front-end, BitBucket, Technical Project Management, Product Development, Webhook, Team Mentoring, Responsive Web Apps, Media queries

# Storage

Elasticsearch, MongoDB, PostgreSQL, MySQL

**EDUCATION** 

# Bachelor's degree in Computer Science

Williams College - Williamstown, MA

2004 - 2008